O.K.
並獲。
OK。
進行。
啊！
而家夠call未啊？
咁而家咧就誒。
而家咧，我就誒。
噉啊，根據在於內務守則第二十二條。
啊，同埋附六四嘅選舉程序。
我哋而家有足夠嘅人數，噉我宣佈啊，今日開會。
啊！提名委員嘅接納，咁而家請委員提名。
永嘉議員，吳永嘉議員。誒，我提名林建峯主席你。係，有冇人和議？
誒，二零一九年、二零二零年立法會會期監察西九文化區計劃推行情況聯合小組委員會主席嘅選舉。
而家咧就係請委員會提名主席一職嘅人選，有效提名係需由一名委員會口頭作出，並需由最少另外一名未獲提名嘅委員會口頭附議。
咁誒，以前第一咧就係誒選舉主席同埋副主席。咁誒，依個主要嚟講咧就係，因為我哋依個係延續㗎，噉我就要諮詢大家需唔需要再重選主席同埋副主席。
唔該。
等等。
而家進行。
而家可以進行投票。
我自己唔可以過二。
誒請工作人員幫手派選票。
好，噉我哋而家進名誒進行筆記名投票。
睇下佢哋有冇其他嘅誒？請問大家有冇其他提名？
嗰邊又話唔夠人喺度開會，兩邊一齊開，我可以。
網民議員，好，阿陳淑莊議員提名黃碧雲議員，有冇人和議？
我數三聲，一、二、三，好。咁而家係兩位候選人。
誒，熒光幕上一號候選人係林建峯議員，二號候選人係黃碧雲議員。
譯志明議員和議係我接受嘅，咁因為我啊接受咗呢個提名㗎啦，噉我就請阿吳永嘉議員主持。
政委員喺選票上邊咧，就屬意嘅候選人嘅編號旁邊咧，就蓋上一個tick號。咁候選人嘅編號次序，我再讀一次嗱，一號係林建峯議員，二號係黃碧雲議員。
有冇人可以？可以啊，可以，可以，提名黃碧雲。可以，可以。啊，陳志全議員可以。啊，黃碧雲議員，你是否接受？哦，我接受。好。誒，仲有冇其他提名？
咁由於係不記名投票咧，請大家咧唔好將選票向其他人展示。請委員將填妥嘅選票合上，誒，但係無需將選票再對接㗎啦。
係。
唔使理。
副主席，我。
好啊！好啊！
穩啲好。
你再搞一搞。
二號。
阿陳志全醫，陳志全醫生，你出唔出嚟？
好，而家請秘書唱票啦。
咁而家有幾多派出咗幾張選票咧？請問。
誒，而家有冇委員未獲發選票啊？
可以請阿譯志明議員同陳志全議員出嚟監督。
誒請個易志明議員投完票啦，同埋阿陳志全議員投完票咧，請出嚟監票啊！唔該。
O.K. 工作人員已發出八張選票，咁而家請工作人員開始收回選票啊！唔該。
誒，如果委員已經填妥選票咧，我宣佈投票程序而家結束。請工作人員唔好再派選票啦。
請委員親自將選票放入投票箱。委員如果未將選票放入投票箱咧，就唔好離開座位啊！唔該。
好，唔該曬。
主持會議。
陳淑莊演。
選呢個。
一號。
二號。
跟住睇下副主席嗰啲。
好，誒而家請監票委員翻翻座位。
嗯，多謝各位委員嘅支持。咁而家咧就係。
誒副主席嘅，咁誒就請，我想請誒委員提名。
O.K.
嚇，得唔得？
有冇？
有冇其他提名？
係係啦。
佢佢已經係。
易志明議員。
黃碧雲議員。
係。阿陳淑莊怡。
如如果冇嘅咧，我哋就請。
陳淑莊議員有有冇人？
麻煩你再講一次。係吳永嘉議員。吳永嘉議員有冇人和議？
啊和議陳志全議員，黃碧雲議員，你接唔接受？接受。
我數三聲，如果冇其他提名嘅咧，就哦有，謝明順，拉完啦，謝明，啊OK。
阿黃碧雲議員，因為你已經誒被提名，你亦都接受咗咧，你係唔可以提名另外一位議員嘅。
誒伍永嘉議員，你接唔接受？誒，我接受嘅，唔該。咁誒，咁而家咧就係有兩位提名嘅，仲有冇其他提名？
誒，佢監。
邊個提名嘅？
好啦。
啊。
正正。
麻煩。
志明出嚟監票。
呢個唔係業績問題喎。
誒，麻煩收票。
咁而家我哋就派選票。
咁咧，就一陣間就請陳志全。
就吳永嘉議員係二號。
咁亦都請兩位提名人。
而家就誒停止派票啦，噉就請。
而家有兩位候選人，黃碧雲議員係一號。
就分別係陳淑莊議員同埋鄭永順議員啦，出嚟監票。
鄭永順議員。
二號。
一號。
睇出九張。
直接我唱票可以。
好啦，而家麻煩請。
噉我話：麻煩請誒秘書負責唱票。
誒正話咧，一共係派出咗九張選票嘅。
啊！
O.K.，噉我哋。
啊！依個係誒政府建議嘅。
府就係提交咗一啲。
問一問誒，議員有啲乜嘢嘢？
而而家就可以進入誒今日會議嘅議程。
二零二零年度嘅會期會議日期同埋討論事項嘅。
誒有關嘅文件咧，已經係再列響議程上邊。
第一個議程咧，就係二零一九年六月十號之後會議後發出嘅資料文件。
嗰個會期咧都擺放咗喺大家面前㗎啦，大家有咩意見？係黃碧雲議員。
意見一啲題目畀我哋去討論㗎。咁而家正正就係我提出嚟畀大家去討論，大家畀意見嘅。
如果委員冇其他嘅意見咧，噉我哋誒可以係處理二零一九年。
喂，主席，我想問下呢一個誒討論事項嘅一覽表嗰個內容係誒邊個同埋點樣整出嚟嘅？
誒，我哋收翻嚟嘅選票咧，誒九張嘅，我哋派出亦都係九張。咁誒票數咧就係黃碧雲議員咧係有四票嘅，吳永嘉議員係五票嘅，噉就吳永嘉議員當選嘅。
噉你作為我哋立法會，我哋而家呢個小組，我哋係立法會，咁點解唔係徵詢咗我哋啊？期望今個年度有啲乜嘢嘢需要喺呢個小組討論，而你坐喺度等政府餵啖飯畀你食啊？
噉我而家宣佈選舉結果，林建峯議員係獲得五票，黃碧雲議員係獲得三票。我而家宣佈林建峯議員當選為本年度聯合小組委員會主席。所有嘅選票將會喺會後喺秘書監督之下咧就銷毀嘅。請林建峯議員上嚟。
你係噉樣領導立法會嘅工作㗎？呢個小組。黃碧雲議員，你都唔係第一次開會㗎啦。正話我講得好清楚，而家正正就係諮詢議員嘅意見。咁如果你唔明白嗰個內容嘅咧，我可以再讀一次畀你聽嘅。你有冇意見啊，黃碧雲議員？啊，主席，我認為你應該係擺議程到。
誒應該要去討論㗎嘛？而家咪就係問你哋咯。啊，噉我所以就問你呢一個表係點樣整出嚟嘅咯？噉你就話係政府訂畀你嘅。嗱，首先咧，我哋係開今年度嘅第一次會議。噉我哋未開會，噉我哋點可以討論咧？咁所以咧，喺未開會之前咧，就政府。
會議日。
O.K.
下次會議。
Okay.
大家有咩意見啊？
誒，下一個事項啦。
嗯嗯，OK，噉我哋就。
即係我哋前後有五次啦，即係今個年度。
O.K.，大家都接受。
號星期一嘅上午十點四十五分。
O.K. 好。網水都因為已經開緊啊嘛。哦，係。
好嘛，OK，咁大家誒就接納咗依個咧，我哋就去。
誒向官員，或者你向我提出嚟，我向誒依個政府誒提出嚟，或者入去下一次開會嘅議程嗰度嘅。
嗱，因為誒意見誒或者個內容咧，其實當有議員係有其他嘅意見嗰陣時咧，我哋都可以。
係，嗰個會議日期，大家有冇問題？係。啊，陳翠莊議員。冇冇特別，我喺度即係睇緊嗰個會議日期，即係因為睇下先嗰個嗱，我哋十一月開、一月開、三月開，我哋今次都比同埋四月同埋六月都開，好似都都OK嘅。
Jeremy。
嗯。
啊！今次。
咁誒，跟住下一個項目咧，就係。
參加我哋嘅會議嘅官員咧。
能夠產生收益，以持續發展西九文化藝術嘅設施嘅。
秘書長介紹一下有關嘅文件，好嘛？好，誒，多謝主席，多謝議員。
重複一次讀出嚟㗎啦，噉啊歡迎各位，噉啊首先或者我請啊。
唔該，柏志高先生。Thank you, Mr. Chairman. In fact, I'm going to ask my colleague to take us through this because it's a very technical presentation.
誒同埋西九文化區嘅代表咧個名單咧就喺各位前邊，咁誒我唔再。
武孟政議員，我舉定手問問題㗎。誒，因為我我有啲事要講。下一一個項目咧就係西九文化區發展進度嘅彙報。噉我哋首先請有關嘅代表入嚟。
咁至於位於二區嘅音樂中心咧，管理局咧就會喺資金允許嘅情況下咧，就優先發展嘅。咁接下來咧，誒我係想請誒管理局嘅總裁柏志高先生用投影片詳細介紹西港文化區發展嘅進度。多謝。
嗱，噉我哋下一次嘅會議咧，就係將會有兩個事項討論嘅，噉就係西九文化區嘅文化軟件發展同埋西九文化區場地營運嘅進度彙報。咁下一次開會嘅日期咧，將會係二零二零年嘅一月六號。
誒主席，誒今日咧係誒消委委員會喺今屆嘅立法會第一次嘅會議。誒咁首先我就住呢一份文件做一個簡短嘅介紹啦。咁呢份文件咧主要係講西九文化區過去一年嘅進展報告嘅。咁誒喺當項嘅設施咧，誒包括起居中心、自由空間咧，今年已。
開放使用，下一個主要嘅設施M加博物館咧，亦都會二零二一年係誒預計會開幕㗎啦。咁為咗加強M加嘅可達性，噉我哋咧就誒建議咧就係喺一個藝術廣場嘅天橋，係唯一一個有蓋嘅行人通道，直接將M加同港鐵嘅九龍站連接嘅。
咁呢個咧，我哋係誒等待緊財務委員會通過相關嘅撥款，咁工程就可以馬上展開。咁至於綜合地庫二區嘅撥款申請咧，亦都對西九嘅文化發展咧係有重大嘅影響嘅，因為喺地庫工程嘅上蓋咧就係酒店、辦公室同埋住宅項目，噉佢呢啲項目咧就能。
hardware。
The main contract final account with the consultant team.
This was announced back in March 18 under the Young Architects and Designers Competition.
Following this announcement, the pavilion was built on a waterfront location in the nursery park.
所以，Zoo Centre was officially opened to the public in January 2019.
The Z2 centre and Free Space have been completed and are fully operational, with very positive results since their opening.
So just a couple of pictures there. You can see inside the main atrium, which is fully open to the public and has been a very popular space.
Also, the tea house, which puts on regular performances daily, I believe, and has also been very popular.
So another smaller project. Members will recall the winning design, growing up, for the competition pavilion, by New Office Works.
And there's a picture of inside the main theatre, or what we call the grand theatre. You can see there has a maximum seating capacity of 1075.
On the far west, we have the Palace Museum and what we call our East Project, which is the Exhibition Centre, the hotels and the offices.
和 further five projects are ongoing under construction, and three projects in the planning or the design stage, including the first of the commercial hotel and operation office and residential facilities.
At West Kowloon, offering very stunning harbour and sunset views, the pavilion's been open to the public since February 19, and has become a spectacular location for small events and activities, and also a popular Instagram location for the young people.
Great, Mr. Stol. Good afternoon, Members. So I'll take you through a PowerPoint today and a few words about progress. So since the last update, WKCA has continued to make significant progress with the delivery of the.
So if I just take you through the slides, we can see here. Obviously, M Plus is in the middle there, nearing completion. The Lyric Theatre, the blue are the sort of future venues. Obviously, the park, which is almost all completed, together with Free Space.
Construction-wise, the project has entered its defect liability period, and the contractor, Hip Hing Construction Limited, are working diligently to rectify the final defects. We're now about eighty-seven percent completed, and concurrently, we're in the final stage of assessing.
I'm pleased to also say that the Z2 has won a number of awards that you can see there since its opening, including the world's hundred greatest places to visit in 2019 by Time Magazine. So I think we're all quite pleased with that.
嗯。
是Fully demountable.
The occupation permit in around April May next year.
And just some people enjoying the sunset from inside.
The goal is to deliver the M Plus building and the occupations.
And you can see there a couple of images in the night time, facing west.
So just a couple more slides. That's a picture facing north.
And they are now contracted directly to the authority, under the management and direction of our management contractor.
By May of this year, all the structural works for the M+ museum and the CSF buildings were completed, and it involved over 100,000 cubic metres of concrete.
The M Plus facade works you can see in the picture here around the tower and the podium are all fully completed. Around two thousand three hundred ceramic panels.
它預計要確保關鍵的佔地許可證，於2020年的第二季，進而引發博物館的開幕，約九至十二個月後。
And within these buildings, plant rooms, building services and a range of interior finishes are currently being installed. And we have benchmarks for all the key finishes following factory inspections.
When Gammons was appointed on the 7th of September, they fully mobilised, and the first challenge was to complete the underground car park, which was located here to the west.
contractually wise，as at the end of October 2019，the authority has issued over 200 novation agreements and deed of transfers with the existing subcontractors who worked under the original main contract.
Such as such has been its success, we gained approval from the licensing authorities to extend its opening by a further six months, and we are also looking at whether or not we can relocate this into a permanent location in the development, as its design is.
So, moving on to the M Plus project, following the appointment of the management contractor back in September two thousand and eighteen to undertake the M Plus project, progress on the construction of the building has been most significant, and the project is on track.
嗯。
and.
came into operation.
An open gallery on the second floor.
The art park will be fully completed.
The third and final phase, including free space and the outdoor stage.
and obviously they're finishing off the podium decks above all of the galleries.
And there's a picture west looking eastwards. You can see the ZTE centre in the background.
所以你見到 podium 已經 completed， and the tower， all the fitting out works is going on in the tower now。
So, moving on to the art park, which is substantially substantially completed.
And just some inside interior shots there. This is what's known as the skylight gallery, providing natural light.
The conservation storage facility in the foreground, a future commercial building there where we will house our head office.
Further to the opening of the West Waterfront Promenade in early eighteen, the second phase including the surroundings of the M Plus Pavilion, the small lawn, the Harbourside Lawn.
This is a key external area that we have a very nice quality finish. What we call these concrete pavers, which will go around the entire external area of the museum.
And the southern part of approximately 300 metres of promenade, and the elevated viewing terrace, where the retail dining and entertainment facilities are located, they have been gradually opening for the public to enjoy since March 2019.
came into operation in June two thousand and nineteen. Whilst the area called the M Plus Lawn, which is to the west of the M Plus building, located above the interfacing car park, that'll be open to the public by the end of two thousand and nineteen, early two thousand and twenty. After which
rectified.
The retail dining and entertainment.
flourishing in the art park.
pushed in to give the whole space within.
Okay, on to the Hong Kong Palace Museum.
The foundations were completed satisfactorily in April 2019.
And currently, we're just going through the phase of a few defects that are being.
towards the end of the year, and another restaurant around the curve there.
And it'll certainly continue to provide green and open space for relaxation, that can be used for organising outdoor performances and exhibitions for the public.
Outdoor events have been successfully held on the great lawn, which is the large area you can see in the in the slide there.
所以你可見，那係一個內部空間，即係自由空間或者黑盒，而那些座位都係可摺疊，所以佢哋可以係出嚟，或者係。
Since then, we awarded the main works contract and handed over the construction site to the main contractor, China State Construction Engineering Limited, at the end of April 2019.
The Hong Kong Palace Museum is coming on very well, and it's fully expected to be completed at the end of 2021 for the preparation of the grand opening in mid 2022.
So adjacent to the Great Lawn here in this slide is free space, and this obtained its occupation permit in March two thousand and nineteen, and the first press event was held in May two thousand and nineteen.
We did have some damage, I think, as we reported before, and disruption to the planted trees from the typhoon Mangkut in 2018. But I can report that all of this has now been rectified, and we have over 2,300 trees.
Facilities are being completed and occupied by tenants in stages, and you can see there in the slide, a lot of these are on the front of what we call the double curve, and I think we have three or four already open here. There's a restaurant up here which should be opening.
So, moving on to the Lyric Theatre Complex.
at the end of 2023 for an opening in 2024.
The L1 contract, which is the excavation, commenced in January 2018.
And it's due for completion somewhere between, end 2020 and 2021.
February 2020，the facade installation work is planned to commence in April 2020.
And as I say, the whole museum is expected to be completed end of 2021 for opening in 2022.
The underground structures for the museum building, including pile caps and the one-storey basement for mechanical plant rooms, are substantially completed.
It's currently subject to some delays, which are under assessment by our contract administrator.
Construction of the building structure has now progressed up to the ground floor, and it's planned to be topped out in around May 2020.
As you may know, the Lyric Theatre complex, the foundations were completed last year.
Both of those contracts were tendered out separately, around a year apart, and they were both awarded to Gammon Construction Limited.
Construction of the superstructure of the Hong Kong Palace Museum has been progressing well, and was around 6% completed at the end of September 19.
所以你可見，呢度係非常廣泛的L1合約，你可見我們稱為ELS，即係挖掘及側向支撐，協助挖掘非常深的孔，約20米深。
External building facade subcontract, which was awarded to a facade specialist in September two thousand and nineteen. We've been doing the preparation of visual mock-ups, and we anticipate that to be ready for final inspection.
And we now have two further contracts, which we call L1 and L2. L1 is essentially for the excavation and the central basement structure, and L2 is the superstructure of the Lyric Theatre itself and part of the underground road.
The L two works contract commenced in November two thousand and eighteen, and the access to the site being given by the L one contractor on time to the L two contractor in September two thousand and nineteen, and Lyric Theatre is due to be complete.
excavation works is completed.
So, just a view there from above.
Very well engineered and quite unique to Hong Kong.
ACE project and that is literally completed.
Finance Committee with this item. So once hopefully we go through.
You can see there the workers which are fixing the base slab right at the bottom of the cofferdam.
Slide there, they sit on these plinths which are already being cast at the bottom of the basement slab.
When they're walking from Austin Station down to Canton Road, so we think this is going to be a very popular link when it opens up.
the financial finance committee, we can then look at awarding this contract. But we have completed the tender process for the Artist Square Bridge.
The purpose of these vibration isolation springs is obviously to, with it being a theatre, is the vibrations that come from the airport express rail link, so.
And overall progress there, you can see here, we are starting to install in the lyric theatre area what we call these vibration isolation springs or system. This is very unique in Hong Kong. We have about 620 of.
That are made overseas, the manufacturing of which is literally now completed, and they are being delivered to site. And hopefully by mid-December, we should have around a third installed on site. But you can see in the previous.
So finally, moving on to the public infrastructure works package, we have a hall road which goes around the Western Harbour Tunnel. This will be used for access to the museum, the underground road, and our future.
The second package for public infrastructure works is for the Austin Road pedestrian linkage system, which connects Zetu Centre to our MTRC Austin Station. This started in May two thousand and eighteen.
And we're now starting the construction of the walls and slabs, and we hope to have this open probably around October 2020. And I think it'll be a extremely well trafficked route. There's a lot of people who at the moment use the ground level.
The third public infrastructure package is for the Artist Square Bridge. I think we've presented this one previously to the joint subcommittee. This has also been through PwC, and we are now on the agenda for the.
嗯。
and is also now on the agenda with the finance committee.
which we've awarded the consultancy to.
The detailed design for the zone 2A is now in progress.
And then the final one on public infrastructure works is a new exit road.
And via a flyover across the western harbour crossing, to Nanchung Road.
The IB zone two, it's obviously between the Z2 centre and the Lyric Theatre.
And the other statutory approvals for the preliminary design of the H.O.R. are currently being sought.
So, building this basement, which will take several years, is very, very critical to us.
The preliminary design phase has been substantially completed, with the underground road gazetted following public consultation in November 2018.
Residential commercial blocks above this basement, and I think everybody knows that this the H O R is obviously key to our future income.
and this is to improve the connectivity of the newly completed Museum Drive, which I touched upon earlier, by connecting it via Hoipoh Road and Lingchong Road to the Route Three.
At the moment, the design consultancy, which is jointly funded by government and ourselves, it commenced in 2017. We've completed the schematic design in 2018, and it was approved in January 2019.
So we're in the study phase, an EIA is being done for this consultancy, and again this one will be subject to public funding, but it would be targeted to commence the construction around the end of 2021.
So the final slide here is for the zone two of the large integrated basement, and this one has also been through subject to public funding. It's been through PwC and.
Obviously, this is a very, very important project for the authority that's been entrusted to us by government. The building of this basement will enable us to push forward very quickly with the hotels, offices and
Income.
Thank you very much.
所以。
And other cultural facilities as well. Yes, thank you.
for the development of our H.O.R. to help us generate.
For key design elements such as the essential basement structure and the communal facilities.
And pursuant to the meeting of the Legco PwC in May two thousand and nineteen.
enhancing community identity and expression, and improving the quality of life for Hong Kong people.
We have carried out ground investigation for the whole zone two, and that was completed in September two thousand and nineteen.
and the tender for the zone 2A area, which is shown on the slide there, was issued in June 2019.
The funding process, the funding proposal, among the other works, is now waiting its turn to be considered by the finance committee.
Completion of the zone two is crucial, as I said, to the sustainability of West Kowloon, and part of the basement will be used.
所以，作為 Authority 運作前進到操作性階段，我們興奮，要扮演一個越來越重要的角色，在提供香港新的機會，就藝術和文化欣賞。
而家就係誒議員發問嘅時間，咁誒首先係毛孟靜議員，啊每位四分鐘。哦，咁長添啊！啊唔該曬主席，嗱真係小橋流水日月如梭，呢個西九文化區咧真係取咗咁多年，實在幾多錢啊！啊嗰個進度啊，大家就～
既熟悉又陌生嘅我自己個人咧，你再提咩戲曲中心英文名叫C.C. Centre，我係到而家都不能接受，係覺得係非常之啊反胃嘅啦。咁而你呢個M加嘅嗰個設計，喂到而家都仍然有人嘈，我知梗係太遲啦。我而家係畀個意。
意見啫，就呢個噉樣嘅設計咧，就真係一塊屏風噉，又亦亦都有人話似墓碑咯。係我覺得真係誒，你係冇其他嘅設計揀咩？咁但係我嘅問題咧就係，我更加擔心嘅咧就係有關啊呢個圍咩牆哇個cover。
都講講啊！
有冇影響？
啊，邊位答啊？係啊，啊啊，主席，誒，首先咧，誒。
誒，即係不能夠解釋嘅，完全係好似打過風之後嘅場面。
Mr. Chairman, I mean, I'm quite happy to try and give a simple response on the cofferdam issue, but it is.
The project has followed all statutory procedures in terms of design approval, construction methodology and the supervision of the works.
去才會取多幾多錢先啊！你又要追加幾多撥撥款，抑或而家已經係零啦？終於小橋流水完畢，係啊！香港人係科款科完了噉，係咪有噉嘅承諾咧？
cover dam，cover dam係係啊，為咩場為演場啊，展場演為演場嚇。我喂，我唔識呢個字添啊嚇。總之就係向下低咧，係掘咗一啲誒excavations，誒，然後就幫你係擋水嘅嗱。你正話噉樣。
暗暗就唔，我唔話你暗沉啦。總之你好smooth咁嚇，好流利讀曬啲嘢出嚟之後咧，就話啦，即係呢啲工程啊，全部O K。喂，但係你隻字都不提話，曾經我哋有晒㗎喎新聞圖片，話嗰度啊有水浸啊啊，有一啲好多嘅。
我就好驚咯！嗰度咁近海係填出嚟嘅，然後你就喺下底再刮，然後就話要嚟防水嘅呢一筆。點解你完全唔提嘅咧？呢個係我問題。而第二咧就係錢銀方面啊，整個西九文化區，你估計仲要啊啊！
就住嗰個維演嗰個工工程咧，誒啊！無議員一陣間咧係下一個下午時會睇嘅，我要三點半離開，所以我要問定嚇。咁另外咧，第二樣嘢咧就係關於個M家嘅設計。一陣間我睇下柏志高先生講。唔需要啊，嗱主席真係嗱，大家唔好噉樣攬住一啲官僚嘅嘢就。
死話等陣先答，而家唔答，唔好意思，我真係要三點半離開。嗱噉樣啦，嗱，因為咧確實咧係下一個題目咧先，即係講有關工程嘅。嗱，既然阿毛議員佢一間有事要早走啲咁多，不如簡單啲啊，你先幫你答一答。多謝主席。噉我首先。
先講講個時間同埋錢一兩句，即係我覺得當大家講誒西九要嘅誒費用啊或者時間表嘅時候，我希望大家記得咧誒西九嗰個誒圖積咧，其實係到到二零一三年嘅一月咧先至定嘅，咁之之後咧亦都去過誒誒個設計。
概念咧，同埋喺個發展潛力咧，其實去到二零一四年嘅接近年底咧，先至喺城市規劃委員會個通過嘅。咁所以期間咧，由零六至到二零一四咧，我覺得呢個嘅延遲咧係唔應該係計喺西九嘅頭上嘅，即係公允少少。咁其他嘅或者嗰個Coverdam嘅懷疑，我請誒西九管理。
The detail is obviously in the second presentation under the second paper. Let me just make a few key points, which I think are really very important. First, at all times, safety of staff and workers is our top priority. That applies both those working on the site and those external to the site.
The authority has can reaffirm very very firmly that there were no serious safety issues or injuries resulting from the incident, and we remain satisfied that the ongoing safety risks on the site are manageable. And let me stress again, and I have said this both publicly and in writing, that there
The authority.
保證嚇。啊，第二位係黃碧雲議員。
not to mention， it is more complicated to carry out construction.
和 nobody goes into this sort of situation without being fully aware of the risks.
Let me stress that below-ground conditions in a deep excavation are always challenging.
地質技術工程師和註冊 general 建築承包商， to carry out statutory duties as required under the buildings ordinance.
Essentially, that's correct. I mean, there will be seepage continuously. There's no way to avoid that, but we don't anticipate flooding.
啊，主席，誒，我想問一問嗰個誒戲曲中心，誒呢度講到就話誒。
since the incident, we've been closely monitoring the situation and working very closely with the appointed works contractors and related statutory authorities.
嗱，二零一九年一月先正式開幕畀公眾使用啦。點解咁快都唔夠一年就進入咗保修期？誒，需要更換同埋修補工作嘅咧，其實嗰啲嘢係係係指啲乜嘢咧？
works adjacent to the harbour, and I'm afraid I have said this publicly before, and I'll say it again. Water seepage is expected, it's managed, and it is dealt with on a regular basis, almost daily.
supports to prevent this happening again. So rather than get into more technical details, which we'll do later, I think I'll end here. Jürga, can I take it to mean that sea page would be unavoidable, but then there won't be any more flooding problems? Is that what I'm getting?
and in addition to the normal third-party supervisors from both the statutory authorities and those employed by management contractors, the authority employs our own team of registered professionals, which includes an authorised person, registered structural engineer, registered structural and
and all responsible contractors are vigilant to ensure that works could be continued carried out safely and effectively, and problems, if any, are quickly identified and dealt with promptly. And indeed, in this situation, although it occurred overnight, the the incident was picked up very quickly and.
within five or six hours was addressed. The complication here, of course, is the subsidence, which occurred outside the area of the L one contract, and that is the issue that we have addressed subsequently by putting in additional cofferdam.
It's normal after after you you take over a facility, there are always going to be small problems that occur, and it's so it is just a minor touch. Generally very minor things like painting that needs to be retouched, doors that don't hang properly. Frankly, if you've ever
係開呢啲標咧。
Third-party contract to do those rectification. It's very normal.
Tendered, the tender will be completed by.
I hope September, October, November of next year. So it's that sort of quarter of next year.
O.K.跟住我想問一問咧，就係誒關於嗰個A.C.E.啊，藝術、商業同埋發展嗰度嗰個項目。
大家喺度誒有少少嘅感覺，好似養草噉樣樣。咁即係有冇啲咩嘢係我哋唔需要呢啲呢啲誒infrastructure喺度，或者係呢啲嘅building喺度，但係都可以做到嘅嘢嘅咧？咁
的金融安排，那係喺事實上係其中一個需要被反駁回，即係喺競標下邊。但係當然係完全符合EFA嘅要求，即係呢個會係BOT，即係Build-Operate-Transfer安排，而我們預期會係。
Had decoration done in your own home, it's the same sort of issues that you would encounter. But under a contract for a construction of this size, there is always a one-year defect liability period, so that anything that is encountered during that first year of operation can be addressed by the contractor, and we don't have to go out to a
咁咧就誒，而家就政府就講，或者西九管理局就講，係會準備嗰啲標書啦。咁呢度其實有冇啲咩你可以話到畀我哋聽？你哋嘅標書嗰個方向或者嗰個財務上邊誒嗰個誒大致嗰個計劃會係點樣樣嘅？即係有咩準則？
Mr. Chairman, yes, indeed, we have completed an expression of interest exercise, and we've had a what we believe is a decent return from a number of different companies that are interested in bidding. We are now processing the tender documentation, which is the next stage of the process, and I hope.
to release the tender by the end of this year or the first quarter of next year. Obviously, we're watching the situation in terms of the economy very closely because this is a very important economic opportunity for us, and we we don't want to release it below a reasonable price. In terms
O.K.誒，主席，即係而家公眾，我諗誒，即係水浸嗰個，我哋一陣講啦。就即係西九咧，其實大家就誒文心文化區咧，大家都係好心急。即係咁多年揼咗咁多錢，但係搞嚟搞去都係搞緊地牢地面嘅嘢。而家都誒，即係除咗戲曲中心係真係真係運作緊，咁其他啲都唔係。
幾多係真係公眾誒係可以用得到㗎？咁誒，即係其實係一路搞緊地下地面嘅建設。即係其實有冇我哋我哋其實西九管理局都已經有一team，即係好請咗好多人翻嚟㗎啦。其實即係我都想知道誒搞工程嘅還搞工程啦，實質上。
誒有啲乜嘢嘅文化活動，即係我哋成日嗰陣時都講，即係點樣可以培養我哋啲觀眾係欣賞文化嘅人，誒藝術嘅教育嘅工作者，誒普及嘅藝術教育呢一紮嘢，似乎我哋都唔係幾見到有啲乜嘢成績做到出嚟，即係變咗好似即係。
Mr. Chairman, in fact, we will be coming back with a more detailed paper on software at the next meeting. But let me just make a few points. We now have operational the park. We've had the nursery park operational for over three years. We have free space operational. We have the M Plus Pavilion operational. In fact, through our programmes called.
但係咧，我哋。
但fail to make the appointment。
我試過打過你辦公室好多次。
The last one, for example, which was I think.
five five artists, five female artists. again, over ten thousand people turned up to see it.
西九管理局咧，響誒舊年咧，確實啊係誒提供過幾個日子嘅，但係咧。
解個情況，好嘛？O.K.跟住落嚟係陳志全議員，係啊，唔該主席。主席啊，我想問下咧，其實就係誒關於。
知道搞緊啲乜嘢嘅，咁同埋我想問咧，就即係其實誒西九嗰個地路大水浸之後咧，我都一路想約，就話去睇下西九文化區嗰個嘅進展同埋情況嘅，噉啊約咗三個幾月都未約到，噉我唔想，我我想知道即係究竟而家嗰個安排會係點樣樣咧？
For example, free space happenings from the recent JazzFest and other programmes. We've had over half a million people come through the West Kowloon to see these programmes over the last four years. So I would disagree with you to say that there are not programming already going on. Just to give you another example, the JazzFest which was held to
two weekends ago I think we had nearly over 14,000 people turn up for that event, so we know that the events that we put on are well received, that they are popular, they're responding to a public need. What we now need to do, of course, is to increase the number of events. The difficulty is, of course.
We're constrained by the delivery of those facilities that are under construction, but I can assure you that we're not waiting for those facilities to be open. We're already working on the programming, the contents. For example, M+ isn't open, but we've been operating M+ Pavilion for something like three years now, running exhibitions.
not only in Hong Kong, we're also operating internationally. We've just closed the Venice Biennale exhibition, where we had over a hundred thousand people through the Hong Kong pavilion, which is again organised by M+. So we are doing an awful lot, and I'll bring much more detail at the next meeting. 啊，主席，或者可能啲宣傳要做好啲咯，因為真係唔係好多人知。
Mr. Chairman, we have actually offered a site visit to members. We've found it difficult to agree with the secretariat on a date. We've suggested, I think, three dates so far, none of which have been accepted. We could do a site visit tomorrow if members are prepared to turn up, but I know how busy you are. I think you're more busy than me because.
攞唔到一個共識，唔緊要，即係既然啊Mr.Pescott啦，正話都提出嚟，隨時都歡迎我哋去，噉我即口講就係咯，但係我哋搞嚟搞去約咗三個幾月、四個月都未約到。噉我我而家咧會同啊Mr.Pescott再急一急，咁揾個時間我哋過去嗰邊啊睇一睇，等啊委員啦多啲瞭解。
呢幾個月咧反修例運動咧，其實誒對於西九已落成嘅項目嘅使用啦，同埋興建中嘅項目嘅進度有冇影響？因為我都知道咧，有一啲誒項目係會取消或者改期嘅，咁如
如果你而家冇一個詳細資料，可以事後即係畀翻一個誒比較詳細少少嘅誒誒報告畀我哋。嗯，我亦想問係其實嗰啲嘅安排係西九決定啦，定係表演單位決定咧噉樣嗱？我我自己都有一個項目叫做拼多咧，都係喺誒西九舉行，都係我哋決定咧，即係個成。
社會氣氛嘅問題係取消咗啦。咁而家譬如我知粵劇噉樣戲曲中心咧，本來夜晚做嘅粵劇咧，而家就改咗三點做嘅，即係大家日日係三點去去睇戲曲。咁呢個我我估都係主辦單位決定嘅。咁呢個問題咧都衍生咗咧，關於啲長租嘅收費問題。而家好多誒演藝團體。
謝偉全議員。
政府 subsidy for these events. That's outside my remit.
Began a few months before opening, and we've already been penciling in and confirming hires into 2020, 2021 and beyond.
一路都有項目，嗰啲項目係你哋西九自己嘅項目，定係已經開始租畀誒其他嘅團體去去誒使用？嗰個租用嘅情況又係點咧？咁唔該。
用The MTR or the transport networks late evening over the last few weeks, and we are always concerned about the safety of people, not just in our venues, but getting to and from the venue. We can't be blind to the reality. Perhaps Alison can comment on free space.
At the moment, it isn't particularly significant, but it's something we're keeping a very, very close eye on because obviously that will affect our delivery of the project. In terms of the impact on performances, yes, again there have been impacts on performances. I think we've
係都希望政府咧係可以有一啲政策係幫佢哋誒噉，亦經營好睏難。有啲項目就係宣傳咗咁啲宣傳費就付諸流水啦。就算嗰啲長租攞翻都係誒無補於事。咁未來咧都係會誒都係艱難嘅。咁西九一向嗰個長租大家都。
覺得係偏貴啦，喺同政府比較啦嚇。咁面對而家呢一個即係困境，會唔會有一啲即係即係可以即係簡單嚟講收平啲，或者係靈活啲，係幫助到一啲表演團體咧？噉樣。第二個問題咧就係關於自由空間嘅嗱，自由空間我都。
想去睇嘅嚇，即係但係都仲係未有機會。咁但係文件嘅第九段咧，就淨係講咗幾句啦，就話三月攞咗許可證，五月就舉行咗首個傳媒活動，跟住咧就話自由空間嘅項目咧就係現正進行更換或者修補。噉我想問，其實佢而家嘅狀態係點？佢係咪一？
deal with the last, I'll deal with the first one, Mr. Chairman. Just to deal with the first points, then I'll ask Alison to deal with the free space one. Effect on work: there have been some slight effects on the works. For example, difficulties getting concrete delivered to the site because of disruption to traffic and what have you. So there certainly has been some disruption.
had to reschedule a number of performances. Usually, that's in conjunction with the hire, because many of these are outside hires. They're not our performances per se, but we always work with them. We have put in place a system to reimburse people who have bought tickets for those events if they can't make it to the rescheduled timetables.
And let me stress, we always try to reschedule rather than simply cancel, because the philosophy is always the show must go on as far as possible. In terms of the detail, what I would suggest is because we have a paper on the software at the next meeting of the of the joint subcommittee, I'll put all that into that paper so you get a comprehensive view on that.
One thing I will say is that for events like Pink Dot, where we feel that the project could go ahead, as we've shown recently with Jazz Fest for example, where it was held, we we work with the organiser because it's obviously not our event to see if there
有任何方式，我們可以 accommodate those those concerns that they have in terms of the rescheduling of programmes. Again, it is up to the the organiser to determine the timing. We've been advising people that we're happy to do matinee shows because, of course, it's becoming quite has been very difficult for people to.
你的問題是關於使用自由空間，自我們開始編程這月，和已經已經是我們自己的程序、租用程序，以及與當地藝術團體合作的程序的組合。和租用租用該場地開始排程，已經在場地打開之前。
Mr. Chairman, if I can just finish on the last question, which is the rent levels. In fact, the rent levels do contain concessions already for certain hirees. For example, in the C2 centre, there are concessionary rates available for C2 users. So that's already part and parcel, and is something we can do. Obviously, I can't comment on the level of.
問。
多謝主席。誒。
on the financial side.
個時間就係話，雖然你話六月到而家噉，你可以咁講咧，就有成五個月啦。咁但係五個月你又褪三個月。
大樓咧最新嗰個目標係二零二零年第二季咧就達到可以攞呢個佔用許可證嘅標準，咁之後咧。
咁咁咁嗰個其實唔係畀人感覺咧，嗰啲係咪好兒戲啊？嗰啲計劃即係無端端咁短時間又可以褪三月，咁呢啲係究竟係我都想知咧，係。
政府嘅文件咧第四段咧提到有關呢個香港新進建築同埋設計師比賽嗰個展亭咧，噉啊呢方面咧嗰個開放之後咧就成為年輕人打卡嘅熱點啦，亦都係誒舉辦小型活動嘅優質場地。咁呢度咧其實我係覺得係好嘅。
因為我多次都希望咧，呢啲噉嘅小型嘅建築工程咧，可以係做多啲比賽咧，畀香港嗰啲誒即係年青人咧可以發揮嘅專長啦。咁呢個正正係係其中一個啦。噉我希望咧西九方面咧，儘量我考慮多一啲。咁其實對成個西九嚟講咧。
其實嗰個誒幫助咧，即係等，尤其是年青人認識咧，就係我覺得係好好嘅。咁呢個呢個第一點咧，我就畀個意見咧呢度。第二點咧，我就即係大家都關注啦，關於西九使咁多錢落咧，梗係關注個進度。頭先好多同事都講呢樣嘢。噉啊，Amplus嗰個。
仲有啲時間咧，就即係實際員工咧就誒，可能再需要啲時間。但係我記得喺六月嘅會議主席嗰陣時講咧，就好似係早一季啲啊，即係即係唔唔係唔係呢個誒第二季啊，係第一季。我冇記錯，第一季。噉我我好擔心咧，即係你你而家講其實。
你哋係咪真係好清楚幾時可以做曬㗎？而家都十一月啦，噉你係咪今次就冇得再褪咧？即係究竟褪嘅原因係乜咧？咁另外大家都關注嗰個就係嗰個誒誒嗰個合約金額嘅問題咧。
咁因為嗰個誒新窗個問題咧，其實而家有冇做過一個粗略估計咧？即係嗰個會超支幾多咧？原本啲五啊九億四千四百萬噉嘅基礎，咁呢方面咧係希望誒西九可以誒講翻畀我哋聽點解決。Mr.Pescott，嗯，Mr.Chairman，let me try and deal with some of that.
Jeremy to supplement. Let me deal with the young architects and design competition. Yeah, I fully agree. I think this is something that we should look at again. I think, frankly, we're going to be trying to take this through this forward in future through a sponsored approach because I think it's a really good opportunity for the community to show support.
for young designers and architects, so we we are still intending to take it forward, but we want to come up with a sponsor that perhaps will look at it over a three or four year period to to show that support. In in terms of further organisations, in fact, this is something that we'll look at definitely.
In terms of the contract amount and the final cost of M Plus, I have said in in this chamber before that that won't be definitively known until obviously we have completed the project and dealt with all the issues arising from it. But I can assure the honourable member that we are working already on the.
Details of what that financial situation may be, I can't really get into it because of course there are inevitably legal issues arising from this. But I can assure you that that work is certainly well underway and is being taken forward. But one thing you're sure that that won't that will be more than
According to the programme.
有一啲時間要去誒。
And it's just a question of how long they take.
Starting in January, we have them programmed out.
跟進嘅，咁儘量咧唔好因為某一啲原因咧嚟到成日改，特別咧將你將個時間表。
誒，前交咗上嚟立法會咧，咁改嚟改去咧，咁議員咧正話都好清晰咁表達咗咧，向依一方面嘅意見啦。咁誒，麻煩你翻去再小心check一check。
5.9 billion. Right, we we have indicated publicly that there will be more. There's no question. Not least, well, perhaps I won't get into it. But yes, I can confirm that that that is just a reality check.
both in terms of time and programme, and this comes to your your second question. Of course, there is a delay in terms of the timing, but we've always anticipated end of first quarter, beginning of second quarter, and we're still sticking to that timetable for the op. But let me stress, the op doesn't mean we can open the museum.
We do need time to fit out the museum, to complete the installation of exhibitions, etc. So that's why we always have known that there would be a nine to twelve month period after OP when we finally open the museum, and that's been programmed in from day one. Chairman, but one thing I'm quite surprised is even that you know.
The latest forecast is the second quarter of this year. You expect to get in the OP right in a position. But I'm just wonder, you know, with just a few month ahead, you can't have a very definite programme to ensure that you know the the project will be completed. I just wonder, you know, in June.
Actually, you mentioned that the expected OPD would be around the first quarter, right, of next year. But now you you have deferred further one quarter. You know, just within five months. It's actually a few weeks rather than another full quarter. Maybe Jeremy can explain. If I could just respond.
The member, I think in June we were reporting end Q1 2020, which was around March. We're actually running probably around four to six weeks, you know, in delay. So we're probably looking at end April, early May, which obviously is.
Q two, but even now sitting here in you know November, we are trying to pull that time back to see if we can you know make it sort of early April time. But we have got the very difficult statutory inspections to go through. They are shall we say a little.
Unpredictable. We think that, you know, obviously we will do everything and use our best endeavours to have the building ready. But there are always issues that can come up in statutory inspections that are a little bit unforeseen, and they may take a little bit longer. But we do hope to have the statutory inspection.
主席，我最主要咧就因為你個時間而家十一月啦嘛，你講出年第一季咁噉，你都唔清楚噉，人哋覺得你好兒戲啦。呢啲噉嘅即係嗰個誒嗰個誒時間表啊，其實應該好準確㗎啦，因為你仲有幾個月啫嘛。講緊咁畀人感覺咧，即係咪餵我我？
中意點就點啦，即係畀人嘅感覺唔好啊！即係呢樣嘢，我希望咧管理局方面咧，即係留意一下咧，即係對呢啲工程嚟講咧，你冇理由係咁誒畀人感覺咧，就樣都都唔清楚。我我諗阿謝元，你嗰個意見好清楚㗎啦。噉我希望啊西九管理局咧，如果有
噉係。
亦都誒。
所謂誒complication咧。
Thank you, Mr. Chairman. In fact, we don't desire any delay in any.
We have to face reality that we are dealing with a very complex building that is not normal in Hong Kong. Nobody builds museums apart from government, and of course they're not subject to the same level of scrutiny in terms of licensing, in terms of operation as we are. So we are facing uncertainty over this. I can't guarantee that the inspections will go.
As smoothly as I would like, and I would be foolish if I was to mislead you by saying, yeah, we can definitely do it by March. I wouldn't do that. Well, I understand that you have the complication, but the Presco, what's the point to give us a date? Because you're going not going to honour it. No, we will try. The key date, honestly, is.
Not the op date, because that is not the date on which the public will gain access. The key date for us has always been the actual opening to the public, and that's the date that I'm working on very hard with my M plus colleagues. 啊，Mr. Pescott，我我諗咧就市議員都明白咧。啊，如果係有一啲
有需要啊，去作出一啲啊調整嘅。咁但係，如果係有呢啲調整啊出出嚟之後咧，或者你哋第二次咧，將有關嘅原因都詳細啲講講畀我哋聽，因為喺個工程嗰度咧，面對咗一啲咩嘅問題，噉啊。
誒唔好次次議員問你嗰陣時咧，就話餵你又改期啦喎，我又唔知點解你噉樣去更改嗰個工程嘅時間等等。好嘛，唔該你。跟住落嚟係最後一位陳淑莊議員。主席唔知有冇第二輪咧？幫我問咗先啦。第一冇啦，冇第二輪㗎啦。哇！咁咁絕嘅，噉樣。因為我哋已經過咗。
我未，因為頭先嗰個介紹都超過半個鐘嘅。如果你有，唔緊要，你問啦，我我會我會桌前咁用畀你問。啊，我我睇到我我睇到頭先你推誒謝偉全議員都好寬鬆。我知我我做桌前啦。得得得，唔使唔使來回啦。我我而家即刻準備問㗎啦。咁咧就誒，首先咧我就想問下咧，關於Amplus嗰啲誒工程合約，因為我諗。
咁可能即係誒誒，西藥管理局都知咧。我到而家都仲收到，最近仲收到幾個咧，係未處理妥當嘅。咁其實佢哋都等咗好一段時候，咁亦都到年尾。我諗對誒好多一啲公司嚟講咧，年尾都係個關口嚟嘅。噉我就想睇下幾時處理得到啦。咁誒，另外咧就係呢一個局方。
方咧就即係喺文件當中就係局方已順利更換咗二百份嘅合約。咁因為我哋以往如果冇記錯嘅話咧，之前咧曾經有提過百零份嘅合約係涉及當時即係新窗而轉手畀金門嘅時候。噉我就唔係好清楚嗰二百份其實佔總體嘅合約係幾多。其實誒誒。
誒係咪已經全部順利完成曬咧？噉我我就係最想問嘅係呢兩點嘅啫。咁同埋誒誒，關於頭先嗰個年尾嗰個，我都希望有一個比較確實嘅情況就而家跟進如何嘅，因為嗰件事都確係一件大嘅事。咁誒，我亦都明白係某程度上局咧，亦都有啲困難嘅嚇。
咁但係我哋都想了解翻究竟幾時先可以處理妥當，因為已經過咗一年㗎啦，差唔多。咁誒跟住咧就係呢一個，主席有一個咧新嘅項目，可能大家都有留意到，就係關於個基礎建設工程。咁頭先咧，阿毛孟靜議員都有講，即係即係小橋流水啊嗰啲噉樣咧，但係咧真係啲錢就流留下咧就。
留完一行又一行㗎啦。咁當然咧，我哋明白咧，誒公共基礎建設工程咧係誒由政府埋單嘅。我先唔講個地牢先啦。咁大家就如果喺翻第十三段開始咧，就有第一組嘅誒建造嘅工程啦，有第二組嘅建造工程啦，跟住有第三組嘅建造工程啦，跟住突然之。
之間喺二零一八年九月咧就出現咗啦。啊，政府同管理局就要展開一條新嘅出出路啊，嚇出口道嘅咁誒，跟住再問誒有顧問啊、設計啊等等。噉我就想問下，即係呢一條路咧誒，其實係咪即係比較近期先至誒確定？
啊！
阿阿阿唐阿唐主席有講話喺西九發展呢個葡萄園，噉我就想問下呢個進展如何嘅？唔該曬。
Mr. Prescott, let me do with the AC and the financial consultant, then I'll ask Jeremy to do with the other two. Thank you. Financial consultant.
下一個再下一個會咧，就會處理呢一個財務誒狀況啊！咁但係係咪攤得凍得滯咧？去到即係你如果二零一九年完成嘅話，其實完成咗，咪點解要攤咁耐咧？咁誒同埋嗰個之前有講過葡萄園㗎，即係。
有呢一個誒誒，需要有呢個建設啦。咁誒而大概即係呢個費用係咪亦都係由政府去監誒即係負擔？因為我見到第十三段都講到好白下㗎啦。噉我想去確認一下嘅。咁誒另外咧就係關於誒頭先阿黃碧雲議員都有問嗰個A C。
E嗰樣嘢咧，誒嗰個項目咧，就係關於嗰啲招標嘅程序誒等等啦。咁但係亦都有關於嗰個財務誒，我亦都聽到阿柏志高先生有講咧，就話係佢哋即係又喺個標書嗰度咧要翻翻嚟要去睇一睇，咁仍然咧係用B O T嗰個方式去處理嘅。咁但係我想問下係咪？
如果冇記錯，係咪都係用翻三十年營運嗰個方式去去做，定係點咧？係咪即係話誒發展商係誒負責誒三十年營運，定係嗰個整個誒睇佢個誒誒成個佢誒翻翻嚟嗰個標書，究竟有啲乜嘢可以誒誒畀到誒誒誒西九管理局？
再去處理咧，即係有冇一個方向咧？咁呢個我想了解一下嘅。咁另外咧就誒係啦，誒嗰個財務誒，因為咧嗰陣時就有講咧，二零一八年第四季咧就邀請呢個財務顧問，噉就二零一九年完成。咁如果我冇記錯嘅話咧，就好似我哋嚟緊係咪？
This is this is a an exercise to look at our long-term financial situation. The report will go into the board first. It's really up to the board to decide what they want to do with it. So, I would expect the the appropriate time for us to to discuss it with members here is after the board have come to a view and we can actually tell members.
what it is they intend us to do. As you know, we do an annual report on our financial situation, and that that would probably be the best time, which is why we have that timing for that. In terms of the ACE, the tendering procedure, in terms of the the timetable, yes, we start from the operational phase of about.
30 years, but then obviously we want to see what the market feedback is, so we are allowing for options around 30 years. Some you know some people may say we need 40, some people can say well we can do it in 30, and we'll look at those as part of our assessment of the of the tenders. But
I think from the point of view of the operation, you also have to add a development period, and that's a key issue because it could be five years or six years, depending on the complexity of the project they come up with. And again, that's something we need to hear as part of the tender. So this tender allows us to assess the market response.
responds to our requirements, and then we take a view on it. But yes, that's all part and parcel of the tender process. So, Jeremy, if you'd like to comment. So, just referring to your questions on M Plus. I mean, obviously, I remember very well the occasions that we met to discuss some of the.
contractors or subcontractors that had approached yourself and and some other members, I think there were around seven or eight cases at the time, and we dealt with all of them. These were subcontractors which were not being taken forward, had decided not to be novated, and I'm certainly not.
aware of any that are still outstanding and any substantial sums of money owed, we we certainly did the best we can to close all the close those out. If there is any final documentation which they are due to be submitting, in order that the final payment can be made, I don't have an update.
Right in front of me, but possibly there is a little bit of documentation waiting. But as far as I recall, most of them had been dealt with fairly satisfactorily. Then I need to call you up. Yes, sure. I'm very happy to come and meet again. Thank you. On the two hundred or so novation agreements, I mean, I think probably when we reported.
OK。
end of 2021, early 2022.
位於四川，當時。
仲有個執漏期咧，頭先都有講，譬如話好似誒誒戲曲中心都有一年嘅執漏期，咁嗰個又會係點樣去處理咧？咁？
我哋而家都係塞緊車嘅喺依度。咁如果係有一啲撥款咧，係唔能夠誒依時。
所以，the the timetable of mid 22 is still set, and we don't we don't we're not varying from that at all.
誒批准交到畀西九管理局嘅，咁對你而家誒手頭上嘅工程會唔會有影響咧？因為正話你講到。
at the time, it may have been a status, if I recall, that we had we had currently done around 100 when we were reporting, but we have actually now done over 200 novation agreements and deed of assignments that have been transferred over to our subsidiary, which is Bluepole's.
Limited, and do I expect any more? Not really. Probably we have a one or two final contracts still to procure, final cleaning things like that. But I don't believe we we will be novating any further contractors that were previously, or subcontractors that were.
So that's M Plus on the new exit road. I don't have too much to say apart from what has been said in the paper. But this is a project that we've been entrusted to do from government or CDD, and we have awarded the design consultancy.
which includes the EIA as well, and I think we're probably around a year or so into the planning side of that project. And as I said earlier, we would hope, subject again to funding, that you know we would start construction around the end.
所以，It's entrusted to the authority. Yes, I see. 好，其實朱生，我以前我做一條係關於誒嗰個叫做誒故宮博物館嘅，因為誒頭先都有講到咧，因為博物館其實唔係真係咁容易去頭先有講到amplas啦，我聽到咁未必咁容易處理，噉我都。
諗緊呢一個故宮博物館，當時係有一個即係希望係二零二二年落成嘅，如果冇記錯嘅話，咁嗰陣時個目標係五年噉。噉我就想，因為頭先有講到嗰啲落成日期同呢個公眾能夠使用嘅日期，噉係咪而家喺誒你哋可唔可以問埋呢一條？即係而家喺你哋嘅誒誒。
誒目標當中係咪真係能夠做得到？誒依一個目標啦，因為其實對我嚟講咧，就即係冇乜特別，即係冇乜嘢嘅。但係我唔想睇到又有一個誒誒壓後嘅情況，噉我就想了解下而家誒嗱，因為佢話預計嘅落成期就係二零二一年，噉係咪一定可以做得到放公眾入去同埋？
我們不預計任何延誤。那個項目是一個非常直截了當的項目，沒有複雜的建築物，沒有大地下室，相對來説是直截了當的建築物。所以我們不預計任何特別的挑戰，就像我們在其他一些建築物上所面臨的挑戰一樣。
誒咁咧啊啊，Mr. Mr. Pasquale，我都有一個好簡單嘅問題，有個好簡單嘅問題想問一問你，因為正話誒議員咧都問到好多工程現嗰個問題，噉啊一誒有一啲款項咧，你係需要立法會撥款嘅，咁如果你知啦，我哋。
啊！
噉啊！
我唔想而家估計。
Thank you。主席，我喺呢度。係，阿秘書長。誒。
完成嗰個工程啦，咁但係依個係同嗰個撥款有冇掛鈎嘅咧？唔該。
陳議員提出過啊，嗰個故宮博物館，噉你話好肯定咁講咧，就話係，我一定會準時啊。
地面嘅誒辦公室啦、酒店啦，同埋其他可以畀西九有一啲恆常性嘅收入，去再營運啲文化設施啦，呢啲先至可以做得到嘅，唔該。
build half the basement ourselves around the zone three, part of zone two A was built for us by the MTR, so the basement exists. It's not as if we could turn around and say sorry, we'll just not build the rest of the basement. If you do that, you don't have a project.
basement， without which we can't build the music centre, the musical theatre, the medium theatre, the education facilities, any of the H.O.R. in that area. Without this funding, we can't build the Artist Square Bridge, which would, frankly.
Mr. Chairman, the the funding approval is primarily for what we call public infrastructure works. That covers critically for us the the sorry, not the Palace Museum because that's funded by the Jockey Club. From our point of view, the key issues are the Zone Two B, Two C and Two A.
have an impact on our operational viability of M Plus the Lyric Theatre Complex and of course the Palace Museum. So these are critical works, without which this project will not be as successful as it as it absolutely can be. And they really do need to be funded. The issue with the basement is particularly important because of course we.
The other point I think I would make is that, without being able to to develop the the commercial facilities in Zone Two B and Two A, the project is going to is going to be even more struggling for funds than it would otherwise have been. So these are absolutely existential for us.
因為其實正如阿柏志高先生講咧，誒嗰個誒地庫嘅工程同埋條橋咧，其實係一個政府應該負責嘅基礎設施嚟嘅。因為喺呢個城市中的花園嘅設計咧，係將啲路咧係由地面搬到去地底，咁所以其實嗰個地庫咧係翻即係好似。
O.K.噉我哋而家咧就進入去下一個議程，就係。
誒，黃碧雲議員正話提出過嗰個參觀嗰個問題。
我未進入去第二個項目之前咧，我都想再回應一下啊。
Thank you, Chairman. Thank you, Members. So this is not just a report on the.
誒演藝綜合劇場同埋綜合地庫項目L One同埋L Two。
commenced shortly thereafter. Those works are now completed, and the practical completion certificate was issued in January 2018.
While that for the remaining works, which is the area to the northwest of the Airport Express and the Tongchong Line, this was issued in February 2018.
月底嘅咁以下，以下咧就係西九管理局咧會用一個誒誒投影片嘅方式向委員介紹翻呢份文件同埋呢個滲水嘅事件嘅。唔該，唔該，邊位介紹？阿阿Professor。
incident itself, it's actually an update on the construction of the Lyric Theatre, and I have my colleague here, who's our general manager for construction, Mr S M Lin, who will help me on the incident itself.
地面嘅路搬咗去地底，而嗰個政府負責嘅。咁大家議員記得咧，淨係個地庫嘅價錢係要一百七十四億幾啊！嚇咁大家會記得當初我哋喺二零零八年畀西九二百一十六億嘅，所以係第一西九唔可能自己食咗呢條數，第二亦都唔公允，因為呢個係政府嘅公。
基礎設施，如果冇嗰度條橋咧，個M加口就個孤島噉嘅。即係就算我哋開咗啲好好嘅展覽咧，其實市民係比較難係經過個工地噉樣行過去嘅。咁所以我哋亦都好，肯請議員咧能夠即係誒，當呢個項目去到誒財委會嘅時候，希望大家可以。
誒，盡快即係當然，我明白議員要審要審視、要審批呢個款項，但係都希望大家明白咧。如果我哋想西九文化發展區咧係發展得比較快咧，我哋必須要有呢個地庫盡早起好，咁先至其他嘅文化藝術設施可以起，同埋留喺個。
其實咧誒西九文化管理局咧係畀咗啲日子我哋嘅。咁當時咧就啱啱七月，我哋咧就開唔到會，所以我哋就冇機會去討論有關參觀西九文化區。咁正話你提出嚟好好嘅，咁所以我亦都要求啊Mr.Pasco咧，咁盡快。
帶畀啲日子我哋，噉我哋盡快安排咧，就去嗰度睇一睇。因為正話啊，委員啦都有好多問題，都係有關而家嘅工程啊啊等等嘅。噉我哋誒一有日子誒收到之後咧，我哋立刻誒知會各位委員，睇下揀一個最多人可以去參觀嘅日子，好嘛？
合作建造工程嘅最新情況，噉啊，都係請秘書長首先介紹一下。誒，主席好簡短介紹。其實七月十二十五日咧，喺西九文化區入邊嘅演藝綜合劇場嘅工地咧，係發生咗水浸同埋地陷事件，誒，引起社會同埋係委員嘅關注嘅。咁西九管理局。
咧係就呢件事件係作咗咗評估同埋跟進嘅。咁今日嘅會議文件咧係有詳詳細列出咧，就係誒估計嘅可能成因、事後嘅跟進同埋事件對於誒演藝綜合劇場嘅影響。咁呢份文件咧係誒誒準備嘅時候係將個發展咧係截至今年嘅十二。
So, just as a reminder to members on the Lyric Theatre, the piling and the foundations which were put into what we call the Zone Three area of the integrated basement, they were awarded on the eleven th of January two thousand and sixteen, and were.
The lyric theatre itself and the integrated basement in the whole of zone three B, and this is the red dotted line you can see on the screen there. This is the whole of the three B area. Consists of two further works packages, and you can see there.
In colours, the brown colour represents what we call the L1 package, which is digging the big hole for the Lyric Theatre and the integrated basement, and the green is the superstructure of the Lyric Theatre itself.
嗯。
The.
end of 2020 and obviously 2021.
Was demonstrated any entitlement in this regard?
Entire lyric theatre complex, but also for the integrated basement.
But as you can see, the lyric theatre actually sits within the integrated basement, as shown in the picture there.
And Tongchong lines, and it's installed above the piles and the base slab, which is constructed by L1.
The L one package, sorry, the L two package, or the second package referred to as L one, was.
was to commence the installation of the vibration isolation springs, and they commence, as I say, in in September, and we hope to have a number of those installed with their plinths by mid-December.
contains the ELS and the excavation works and pile caps, and it's adjacent to Austin Road West, and it also has the essential basement structure, as I said, which receives the Lyric Theatre. The L2 contains the superstructure itself and includes all the structure, the building services, the architectural finishes for the.
Notably, as I highlighted in my previous presentation, the LTC building is supported by a structural isolation spring system, and this is part of the L two contract, and it stops the vibrations emanating from the Airport Express.
Currently, the the brown area or the L1 package, it was awarded in January two thousand and eighteen, and we've currently suffered some delays due to seepage in the cofferdam, and we will touch upon, or my colleague will touch upon, one of the incidents.
That recently happened in July. So the final completion date of L1 is currently under assessment. We've had claims submitted from the contractor and they are being assessed by a contract administrator. But we anticipate it's somewhere between.
The critical message here is the Lyric Theatre itself, and the Lyric Theatre has already the contractor has already had access to site. That was in the middle of September this year, and the first activity under that L two contract.
So the contractor has for L one has currently submitted, as we've reported in the paper, there some claims for delay. However, as of the moment, we cannot report that the contract administrator has awarded any extension of time.
Since July two thousand and nineteen, when we had the seepage incident, considerable progress has been made in the recent months with concrete blinding and reinforcement concrete works. This has included the construction of the basement pile caps, which has enabled.
嗯。
administrator。
and then。
to hold the coffinum， and then we do more excavation， more struc。
So-called are been have a lot of temporary work holding the cover them, yeah.
六百三十 in total, almost all finished manufacture, and we will progressively install these.
The first L2 works, as scheduled and approved in the main works programme, and it actually commenced three weeks ahead of schedule.
In addition to progressing the installation of the isolation springs, the L2 works contractor is focusing on design development and procurement, and currently they have around 140 staff on site.
So this is a view on inside the coffin. And as you can see, on the right hand side, this is the what we call pile cap. It's been constructed. On the left side, we still need to do the the foundations.
Okay, this is just a simple animation just to demonstrate how do we construct this cover dam, and what what are the pipe power and the grouting. So just to show you how do we constructs this basement.
As of mid 2019, around 53% of the vibration isolation spring plinths and anchor bolts have been cast, and as I say, the first spring was installed on the 17th of November, 2019.
With access to the site that's been allowed, the L two contractor will aim to integrate their programme with the remaining works under the L one contract in order to mitigate some of the delays. But the programme remains under review by the contract.
Progress is being made with the coordination between L one and L two, and currently we're going through things like visual mock-ups and shop drawing production. So I'll hand over to my colleague who will talk a little bit more specifically about the L one incident.
Chairman and members, this is the aerial view. Just to demonstrate to you, the site is on the top left. You can see there's the airport express line there, and then this is just the working platform, and this coffeenum.
So this is the pipe power we insert into the ground. It's about minus thirty, it's about thirty metre deep into the from the ground level. And then this is the crop curtain we're talking about behind it. We we install this crop curtain.
To prevent water from going in, once we done that, we start the excavation. We go to a certain level and then we put some temporary steel there to hold the coffinum, and then we go to next stage. We excavate more and then we install another layer of struc, we call it.
OK。
嗯。
yeah，so now I。
If this is not been dealt with,
This is the stage. This is how the sequence of work.
more excavation, more struck, so.
Okay, this is how the the sinkhole happen.
所以，what happened was somewhere in the
Once we done that, we start doing the the pile cap. This is permanent work. This is the pile cap construction.
get bigger until one stage that this wall is so big and it cannot take the load, the weight of the soil above it, and it will collapse.
The pocket will occur inside the outside, sorry, outside the corium, and the pocket you get bigger.
Moving on, this is the how do we treat this incident? So what we do is the the sinkhole is happened on area two, which is the bottom right here.
Okay, this slide here we want to show you a simple animation, just to demonstrate you how the sinkhole happen. Why is it happen? How the water going in? So you can see from here, the this light colour blue is represent the the
水，所以外面的礦坑的水位表是 quite high， is about three meter from the ground level. and for the inside, we have a pumping system. we pump the water out. so the in in the design is meant to below the formation level. okay.
Cloud curtain there's a small leak, okay, and it's happened at night time. So the water keep going into the into the inside cofferdam, okay. When the water go in, you bring a very fine sort of sand to go inside to the cofferdam.
Okay, the the the incident area is here, and we our whole site we divide into area one, two, three, four. We discuss with the statutory authority how do we move forward this job even though we have incident on.
Area two.
August。
then area three.
Building Department， so that
作為第二個層級的防禦。
The activities we we have mapped out.
behind the incident area.
Okay, so we go on every one. We can carry on doing our construction of the power cap.
Okay， and for your information， the area four， we are still on the stoppage order。
另一 words， that we need to finish the additional pipe wall， and then we need to submit the investigation report to the
very close to the airport link, so we have a different strategy, a different enhanced work or mitigation work to that need to be demonstrate to the building department.
We have a difference. No, let's go down here. Area two, area two, because of the sinkhole, what we what we did is we propose to the building department. We have an additional pipe wall.
start work on area one. So what we did is we submit some proposal, some remedial work, some enhance work. So we at the end the building department agree for us to resume only twenty third of.
所以what we did is we draw out, we have a route map. We talk to the building department. How do we overcome this with this incident and error too? So we demonstrate to the building department that we can.
and then we concentrate, we divide again on the area three. so the area three we have to discuss further with the building department, because this area, as you can see on the south side is the Victoria Harbour, on the left side is.
When we finish these two, then we will review all the report, the testing, and before they decide whether we can resume work. That is the general approach. This table here is just to show the line of events. Yeah, the date and the events.
拆 later on.
And then.
Okay.
嗯。
Okay, this slide just to show you.
Thank you. Okay, thank you.而家係誒。
Alright, so the the white colour one is just to be done.
議員發問嘅時間，啊，首先係黃碧雲議員，四分鐘唔計。
the the light green is this is before the incident happened. This is the power cap was constructed and.
And then the the the green this coming up is since we resume work, we have more or less completed so-called the the northern part of the coffeenum.
This is just to let the members know that Garmin have reported the incident to the insurance. They are having their discussion and going through the.
Give you another minute to finish it because we have to finish today's meeting at four thirty. Point B basically, Jeremy has just mentioned that at the moment the contractor Garmin is putting 114 days delay.
啊，主席，我就誒想問一問啦。呢度就政府就誒誒西九管理局喺文件講就話係漏水啦。咁但係現場其實我都誒都有落去睇嘅。咁當時其實見到大水浸，即係即係個人頭咁深㗎。噉我想問咧就係誒。
This is just a repeat and this thing we need to do to resume the area for the two things as I mentioned before, finish the the clutch pipe power and then finish the investigation report and and then we are looking into how we're going to speed up the the work to to do some catch.
okay this is just a image to show you this is the vi vias bearing it's been one hundred percent manufactured from Germany we have about forty seven percent delivered to site and this is just a snapshot just showing you know when we we pour the concrete we can just position into place.
即係嗰個而家嗰個詳細嘅調查報告咧，政府就話誒要同屋宇署嗰邊傾嘅。噉我想問就係，即係誒可唔可以幫我哋攞嗰個調查報告啊，畀我哋睇一睇，即係究竟成件事嘅發生，即係點解會係誒造成嗰個嘅誒？
Mr. Pescott.
啊，邊位？阿彭小姐。
係通常個處理手法係點樣嘅？係。
誒，可唔可以詳細少少答一答咧？呢度。
通常嘅處理手法，你唔係就應該高度透明咯？
圍堰牆水浸啦，咁究竟係嗰個嘅誒？
究竟商量嗰啲係啲乜嘢嘢，同我頭先問嘅嗰啲問題係咪有關嘅咧？
你呢個地庫有冇涉及係公堂支付嘅咧？即係究竟係係個監管出咗問題定邊度出咗問題？冇理由，議員係完全唔知道嘅。噉我哋我哋點我哋點樣？你點樣向即係立法會呢邊問責咧？
但係咧就住嗰個合約嘅內容，究竟誒涉及嘅誒個風險嘅攤分，但係初步嚟睇咧，西九管理局同埋合約管理人咧回覆我哋咧，都係呢個風險咧仍然係喺個誒承建商嗰度。多謝主席。咁即係咪金門要負責啊？就成件事。
設計嘅問題啊，亦或係嗰個物料嘅問題啊，亦或係施工嘅問題啊，亦或係咩嘢咧？咁咁同埋邊個係要為誒呢一個嘅水浸誒工程出現問題係負責嘅咧？咁咁金門咧就講話要延期一百一十四日噉。
而家誒西九管理局好似就話：覺得唔好convincing咁咁咩意思啊？咁即係即係佢佢係咪？你認為你你唔批佢延期噉就佢就要追翻，而又可以追得到咧咁咁誒？如果佢做唔到咁咁又點咧？你係咪喺合約上邊有個懲罰機制，話你你延期我唔批准你，但係你延期。
嚇追唔到進度，你係會有懲罰，抑或係點樣樣咧？咁咁同埋有冇涉及嗰個工程嘅超支？咁呢扎嘢咧，我哋而家手頭完完全冇資料，我哋又冇嗰個調查報告。噉我諗我我覺得係比較合理咧，係畀委員睇到嗰個調查報告，同埋而家政府話同屋宇署係會誒商量。咁夠。
主席好。誒，阿應小姐係主席。咁誒，啱啱誒管理局都講緊啦，其實佢個調查報告咧，亦都係同緊誒誒屋宇署咧係仲係研究當中嘅。咁因為依個牽涉啊嗰個屋誒建築物條例嗰個規管裏邊啦，噉我都要係誒問一問誒屋宇署咧，究竟依啲嘅調查報告咧。
主席，多謝啊，黃議員嘅提問。其實就住咧呢個誒調查報告一啲內容咧，其實西九管理局喺佢文件裏邊嘅執行摘要裏邊咧，第十四段咧都有一啲交代咧。而家初步咧，佢有啲誒誒諗法咧，嗰個誒初步調查嗰個誒情況嘅。咁咧就可能相信咧誒。
誒，我哋會同屋宇署再去跟進，去落實依一個調查報告嘅內容嘅。噉就住誒，而家誒西九管理局咧，佢哋而家嘅誒認為咧，即係初步嘅睇法咧，因為一個誒依啲水浸嘅情況咧，好多時候喺合約裏邊呢啲風險咧，都係一個誒承建商需要承擔嘅風險嚟嘅，所以咧佢。
合約管理人咧，其實而家就住呢個風險同埋呢一啲合約嘅情況咧，已經係作出一個誒跟進。噉我哋其實誒，同工程拓展處咧，亦都紮成咗西九咧，會將呢個報告咧，盡快咧同屋宇處咧就去誒落實嗰個誒調查報告嘅，同埋咧亦都紮成咗佢哋咧同誒合約管理人咧，盡快。
係咪噉嘅意思啊，黃議員？
誒，主席，我仲有一個問題㗎，得問唔得啊？
有有問題嘅時候，鼻震功能出現問題嘅時候，噉你你哋點啊？到時。
咁下邊有呢啲噉樣嘅避震器，咁呢六百幾個避震器裝咗落去之後，係咪永久啊？
唔係我，我係問邊個要負責啊？成件事呢個唔係一個單純嘅意外嚟㗎嘛？係咪啊？
咁咧就確保咧嗰個損害對個地盤嚟講咧係最少嘅。多謝主席。噉，主席噉你幫我追翻嗰個調查報告，我哋翻嚟先研究下點樣跟進啦。好。
即係拆咗上邊嗰嚿嘢，抑或你有有秘道落到去下邊可以換咗啲有問題嘅咧？我唔知啊，即係我唔係工程人員嚟嘅，即係即係我想知道係點搞嘅啫。
多謝主席啊！多謝黃議員嘅跟進。負責咧係咪嗱？而家整翻好佢啦，咁即係話政府或者西九管理局唔需要付出額外嘅補償。
O K，誒呢呢個比較簡單啲嘅，嗱嗱我誒即係我我申報先啦，我唔係工程師嚟嘅，所以我都係跟大家學習嘅啫。我想問嗰個嘅誒地震嗰個。
誒多謝主席啊，多謝黃議員跟進啦。頭先都有講咧，而家我哋都係睇緊個初步嘅調查報告。我哋成件事咧仍然需要咧同屋宇署咧落實咗嗰個誒事發嗰個成因啦。不過我哋而家最主要嚟講咧，就係我哋要確保咧個地盤咧係可以繼續去去施工啦，同埋可以繼續去誒做翻嗰個誒工序喺度。
誒嗰個叫做彈簧隔震器，噉我知道誒，即係文件嚟就係話要嚟即係隔開地底嗰啲可能鐵路啦嚇，嗰啲噪音同震動。咁呢度有六百三十個嘅，咁而成個誒嗰個New York Center係坐落喺呢呢嚿地庫底下。
咁即係唔需要話啊！如果佢即係佢彎咗，譬如六百卅個裏邊彎咗十十個percent噉，噉你噉你上邊嗰嚿嘢點啊？定係起好咗放咗落去，唔可以成嚿吊走㗎嘛？係嘛？你唔係諗住做大型貨櫃噉樣可以抽走，係咪即係永久喺度㗎啦？咁如果佢冇function或者佢有。
Okay, Mr. Stol, thank you, Chairman. I just would like to very briefly go back to your earlier question, though. About you asked specifically about EOT on the leakage incident. I mean, we've said in the paper there that just for record purposes, the contract administrator has not yet awarded any extension of
Time yet for this incident. Although we have received a submission from our contractor, it's currently under assessment. But as of today, no EOT has been awarded to Gammon for this incident. If EOT is not awarded, there are penalties under the contract.
For time, so that's just for record purposes on that. To answer this point about the vibration isolation springs, it's actually fairly simple technology. It's not a sort of sophisticated system. You wouldn't have to be too much of an engineer to go down on site and we could show you how it works.
But they are installed permanently. They will sit under the building permanently. There's an area to inspect them, you know, just to to see, you know, whether they sort of grease them or oil them or that sort of thing over a regular period. But it can they can be accessed.
incident.
Mr. Stoll。
風險咁呢個純粹我意見，多謝主席。
喺個監工、監管、驗收工程方面咧。
啊，或者有啲工程方面嗰個驗收啊、監管方面咧，係。
Throughout the lifetime of the building, but they are a permanent installation for the building.
事喺度咧，呢方面咧其實好多因素應該考慮到，咁先有㗎。你唔好話即係喂好複雜啊！我噉啊處事講畀你聽，本來下個禮拜得㗎啦，又再褪一個禮拜。
requesting or that he has to demonstrate his entitlement to any extension of time. If he fails to demonstrate any entitlement,
臨時嘅，咁但係個作用喺度，因為你頭先都講，你你方便成個即係地地庫嘅挖掘啊、支撐個方成個系統咧，佢又重要。
O.K.啊，跟住係謝偉全議員。係多謝主席。好簡單，即係當然咧，即係關於誒七月二十五號嗰個事件咧，嗰個責任誰屬啊，或者嗰個誒即係係咪有E.O.T.啊等等咁呢個即係各方面喺呢方面咧，就根據嚇嗰個。
資料啊，同埋合同方面咧，大家去係就呢樣嘢去研究。咁呢樣嘢咧，我都希望咧，將來即係有結果咧，我哋都知啦。即係究竟係嗰個責任水屬，包括嗰個時間啊，同埋個造價咁呢樣嘢。但係我我我如果冇記錯咧，關於個呢個圍墻呢個噉嘅。
噉我反而咧，即係誒記得好似佢誒發生呢啲問題嘅時候咧，唔止一次嘅嚇。咁當然即係有陣時你好難估計。不過我都希望咧，即係有關誒，即係西九好或者係政府睇嗰個誒，對於成個工程。
經過呢啲噉嘅事件，因為呢啲事件會影響你成個進度啊嘛，亦都可能係咁咧。你頭先講根本你成日都話，我估計唔到嗰個誒員工日期好或者幾時好攞O P。雖然你個表裏邊有講嘅咧，十一月三十號咧就呢樣嘢你可以B A十四咧，可以擺誒。
可以可以可以可以誒誒呢個誒交畀誒澳宇處啊噉樣，我都好擔心咧。即係你你呢樣嘢係咪準咧？因為畀我感覺咧，就係好短嘅時間，你哋嗰個估算咧都都因為話複雜啊，所以我哋冇辦法啦。咁所以頭先我就即係覺得呢樣嘢好似係你有咁多專業人。
喺呢度咧，我希望咧，即係純粹一個意見，係咪可以做好啲咧？咁如果唔係，你每一次有個事件發生咧，就變咗到時唔多唔少咧，你都就算話係唔係誒，即係誒西九方面負責咧，但係始終都係會阻慢咗工程，同埋某程度亦都增加咗。
I mean, just to reiterate that you know, there's mechanisms under the contract. You know, when when incidents happen and when delays happen, and we have a contract administrator that's there to make assessments. If we have an incident, the first thing is for the contractor to submit particulars of that.
唔該曬。
嗰啲問題咧，都係。
大家都想了解多啲點解會發生？好啦，而家做好咗之後。
誒有依依個倒塌嘅事情發生，同埋誒即係以後點樣可以確保個安全？
最主要誒同埋關心個安全嘅問題嘅嗱，咁今次而家做做好咗啦，咁誒。
O.K.噉就唔唔該曬誒今日嚟參加依個會議嘅政府官員同埋西九管理局嘅有關成員。
就誒，而家就其他事項，委員有冇其他事項提出？冇，咁咧我就誒宣佈今日嘅會議結束。多謝各位。
We have to deal with it, and we have to understand why it's happened. The incident in July was certainly more significant, and hence that is why a full report, full investigation report, was submitted to BD.
I'm actually very happy to do that, but the best way, as I've suggested, is actually to have a site visit. We can describe on the site exactly what happened, because you know this is very technical. And and members, really, I would urge you to to agree an early date for a site visit, and we'll do the full explanation there. I think it's the best way.
For an extension of time, then under the contract, he has to catch up the works, and that might be more resources to achieve the original deadlines. Otherwise, he faces penalties. If obviously the contract administrator is convinced that.
The contractor has made submissions which show an entitlement. Then he will award him the necessary extension of the time. So we constantly monitor the progress of the works, but it does depend on the submissions that we receive from the contractor to.
Demonstrate his entitlement. We have had small water leakage or seepage incidents throughout this contract, as was said earlier. A cofferdam is not a watertight structure. It does allow for water seepage. So when it occurs.
誒，最後我想簡單問一問啦，因為正話議員都啊提問過有關嗰個誒倒塌個問題。其實我睇一睇個範圍都唔細㗎。咁誒，我亦都睇到啦，西九管理局啊都做咗好多嘢啊嚟到復修。咁誒，其實議員問。
會唔會誒再發生，或者第一次發生嗰個原因會唔會有有一啲所謂未知數？以後會再發生嘅咧？噉我諗議員咧都係想向呢一方面多瞭解嘅。噉啊，都希望啊Mr.Pascal啦，即係可以提交多一啲資料，等我哋瞭解多啲點解會。